Guide to the Robert Martin Collection on Gay Sexuality and Education MSS.499
Fales Library and Special Collections
Robert Martin Collection on Gay Sexuality and Education
1935-1986
1960-1970
Fales Library and Special Collections
Martin, Robert
Poynton, Jerome
MSS.499
4 Linear Feet in 4 record cartons
Robert Martin (1916-2015) served in the U.S. Army during World War II and was Chief of the U.S. Army Research Laboratories Sci-Tech Information Division in Natick, Massachusetts for 25 years. He lived the majority of his life in West Virginia. This collection contains gay erotic pulp novels; non-fiction books on homosexuality and sexual education; and a small collection of erotic images of homosexual and heterosexual activities.
Arrangement
The collection was been arranged by a Fales student worker by item type. The pulp novels and non-fiction books are listed separately, in alphabetical order by author's last name, followed by the one folder of photographs.
Biographical Note
Robert Martin (1916-2015) was born in Ohio, and eventually moved to Wheeling, West Virginia. Martin acquired degrees from both Bethany College and Vanderbilt University, and served in the U.S. Army during World War II. He was Chief of the U.S. Army Research Laboratories Sci-Tech Information Division in Natick, Massachusetts for 25 years. He eventually moved back to West Virginia, where he passed away at the age of 98.
Source: "Robert Martin."; "The Intelligencer. Ogden Newspapers," 9 February 2015. Web. 30 March 2017. http://www.theintelligencer.net/obituaries/2015/02/robert-martin/
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers. Appointments are necessary for the use of manuscript and archival collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was donated by Jerome Poynton in August 2016; the accession number associated with this gift is 2017.089.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains gay erotic pulp novels from the 1930s to the 1980s; non-fiction books covering topics such as homosexuality and society, sexuality, and sexual education from the 1940s to the 1970s; and a small collection of undated photographs, playing cards, and photographic reproductions of erotic artwork of homosexual and heterosexual activities. This collection illustrates the informational and recreational material accumulated by a gay man living in Massachusetts and West Virginia during the 1950s through 1980s.
Custodial History
An unknown individual purchased Robert Martin's estate after his death in 2015, discovered this collection of material, and gave it to Jerome Poynton, who then donated the collection to the Fales Library in 2016.
Gay erotica.; Photography, Erotic.; Gay men -- Sexual behavior.; Gay erotic literature.; Sex instruction -- United States; Erotic stories, American; Homosexuality -- United States.; Sexual health; Poynton, Jerome
- Anderson, Robert. Tea and Sympathy, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Atkinson, Hugh. The Games, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Burgess, Preston. Confessions of a Married Man, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Chorier, Nicolas. The Dialogues of Luisa Sigea, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Cione, Jack. What do you say to a naked waiter?, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Cleland, John. Memoirs of a Coxcomb, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Cray, Ed. The Fifteen Plagues of Maidenhead and Other Forbidden Verse, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Davidson, Chris. A Different Drum, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Davidson, Chris. Go Down, Aaron, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Douglas, Dean. Man Divided, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Dowd, Harrison. The Night Air, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Forberg, Friedrich-Karl. The Manual of Exotic Sexualia, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Harmon, Jackson. Perverted Psychologist, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Hirschman, Jack. Teleny, or the Reverse of the Medal, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Hunter, John Francis. The Gay Insider, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Jackson, Charles. The Fall of Valor, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Jadaway, J. J. 7 Erotic Minutes, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Jourdan, Eric. Two, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Kent, Nial. The Divided Path, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Knight, John. The Story of my Psychoanalysis, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Kovar, Dallas. One to Share…, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Lindop, Audrey Erskine. The Tormented, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Little, Jay. Maybe—Tomorrow, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Martin, Cort. Bolt: Six-Guns and Silk, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Niles, Blair. Strange Brother, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- The Pearl: A Journal of Voluptuous Reading, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Purdy, James. Eustace Chisholm and the Works, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Rogers, Rosemary. The Insiders, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Rose, Dustin. Fiery Fists, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Sanderson, Douglas. Dark Passions Subdue, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Shrader, Bert. Gay Tutor, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Taylor, Dyson. Bitter Love, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Tellier, Andre. Twilight Men, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Tesch, Gerald. Never the Same Again, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Therese, Marie. I'm for Hire: The Memoirs of a Prostitute, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Wagman, Paul. Hollywood Homo, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Watson, J. The Sexual Adventures of Sherlock Holmes, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Wilhelm, Gale. We Too Are Drifting, 1935 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Wylie, Philip. The Disappearance, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Brecher, Edward and Ruth. An Analysis of Human Sexual Response, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Caprio, Frank S. Female Homosexuality: A Modern Study of Lesbianism, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Cory, Donald Webster and John P. LeRoy. The Homosexual and his society: A view from within, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- d'Arcangelo, Angelo. The Homosexual Handbook, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Edwardes, Allen and R.E.L. Masters. The Cradle of Erotica, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Geddes, Donald Porter and Enid Curie. About the Kinsey Report, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Geddes, Donald Porter. An Analysis of the Kinsey Reports on Sexual Behavior in the Human Male and Female, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Gordon, David Cole. Self-love, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Greenblat, Bernard R. A Doctor's Marital Guide for Patients, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Hegeler, Inge and Sten. An Adult View of Love and Sex, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Jorgensen, Christine. Christine Jorgensen: A Personal Autobiography, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Kronhausen, Eberhard and Phyllis. Sex Histories of American College Men, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Lindsey, Hal. The Late Great Planet Earth, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Mansfield, Jayne and Mickey Hargitay. Jayne Mansfield's Wild, Wild World, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Marlowe, Kenneth. Mr. Madam: Confessions of a Male Madam, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Masters, R.E.L. The Homosexual Revolution, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Patai, Raphael. Sex and Family in the Bible, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Rogers, James C. Sex Outcast, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Ruitenbeek, Hendrik M. The Problem of Homosexuality in Modern Society, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Schultz-Larsen, J. The Morphology of the Human Sperm: Electron Microscopic Investigations of the Ultrastructure, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Shepard, Martin. Ecstasy: The Moneysworth Marriage Manual, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Stearn, Jess. The Grape Vine: A Report on the Secret World of the Lesbian, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Tobin, Kay and Randy Wicker. The Gay Crusaders, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Photographs, undated (Box 4, Folder 8)